<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
  <?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="rfc2629.xslt" ?>
  <!-- generated by https://github.com/cabo/kramdown-rfc2629 version 1.0.26 -->

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
]>

<?rfc strict="yes"?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<?rfc iprnotified="no"?>

<rfc ipr="trust200902" docName="draft-koster-t2trg-hsml-00" category="exp">

  <front>
    <title>Media Types for Hypertext Sensor Markup</title>

    <author initials="M." surname="Koster" fullname="Michael Koster">
      <organization>SmartThings</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>1281 Lawrence Station Road</street>
          <city>Sunnyvale</city>
          <code>94089</code>
          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>
        <phone>+1-707-502-5136</phone>
        <email>michael.koster@smartthings.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date year="2016" month="July" day="10"/>

    <area>Internet</area>
    <workgroup>Thing-to-Thing Research Group</workgroup>
    <keyword>T2TRG, Web of Things, Hypermedia, Semantic Interoperability</keyword>

    <abstract>


<t>The scale and scope of the worldwide web has been in part driven by the availability of HTML as a common serialization, data model, and interaction model for structured resources on the web. By contrast, the general use of appropriate hypermedia techniques for machine interfaces has been limited by the lack of a common markup format for serialization and exchange of structured machine resources and sensor/actuator data which includes or embeds standardized hypermedia controls. Machine optimized content formats exist for web links <xref target="RFC5988"/> <xref target="RFC6690"/> and for data items <xref target="I-D.ietf-core-senml"/>. Structured data which contains both links and items is known as the collection type. This draft describes media types for representation of machine resources structured as collections. A common data model is described with a representation format that uses a common set of reserved keywords to expose hypermedia controls, which inform clients how to perform state transfer operations on resources. The underlying assumptions regarding transfer layer processing are specified in this document. The HSML media type described in this document is compatible both SenML and with CoRE Link-format by reusing the keyword identifiers and element structures from these documents in the base representation of the collection.</t>



    </abstract>


  </front>

  <middle>


<section anchor="scope" title="Scope of this document">

<t>This is a broadly scoped document which specifies representation formats, data models, interaction models, transfer mapping, URI processing, and some extensions including actions and bindings.</t>

<t>The features listed above and new features may be specified and extended as needed in other documents which refer to this document.</t>

</section>
<section anchor="overview-and-use-case-requirements" title="Overview and Use Case Requirements">

<t>Use case requirements include the following.</t>

<t>A standardized way to expose self-describing resource representations using embedded links and link annotations.</t>

<t>A standardized way of organizing and interacting with resource instances using hyperlinks.</t>

<t>A standardized encapsulation of resources for modeling things, capabilities, groups, indices, and other common structures.</t>

</section>
<section anchor="model" title="Data Model and Interaction Model">

<t>The HSML data model consists of collections containing links and items. An instance of a collection is identified by a URI.</t>

<t>Items are data elements, either within the context the collection, or outide the context of the collection. An instance of an item is identified by a URI.</t>

<t>Links are standard web links as in <xref target="RFC5988"/> or <xref target="RFC6690"/>.</t>

<t>Items are identified by links in a collection. An Item may only be in the context of one collection, but may be identified by any number of links in any number of collections.</t>

<t>Links in a collection may point to items within the context of the collection or they may point to items external to the collection, on the same server or on other servers.</t>

<t>Items in the collection that use the SenML data model may be embedded in the collection and transferred either along with the links or separately from links.</t>

<section anchor="normative-representation" title="Normative Representation">

<t>JSON formatted examples are used in this document to illustrate normative and informative concepts. Representations in other formats may be derived from the JSON representations.</t>

</section>
<section anchor="links" title="Links">

<t>Links follow the specifications in <xref target="RFC5988"/> and <xref target="RFC6690"/> with extensions to implement actions and monitors as described in this document and any referencing extension documents.</t>

</section>
<section anchor="collections" title="Collections">

<t>Collections contain one or more links and extended links, and may contain data items referred to by the links. A representation of a collection may contain both links and data items.</t>

</section>
<section anchor="link-embedding" title="Link Embedding">

<t>Link embedding emnables the transfer of more than one item in a collection using a single transfer operation.</t>

<section anchor="batch-operations-on-multiple-items-in-a-collection" title="Batch operations on multiple items in a collection">

<t>A collection of items enables operations on more than one item at a time by exposing a structured a representation of multiple resources in the collection.</t>

<t>Applications may select resources by using URI parameters, and transfer representations of multiple resources using the SenML multi-item format.</t>

</section>
<section anchor="collective-operation-on-groups-of-linked-resources" title="Collective operation on groups of linked resources">

<t>Resource links in the collection may specify group transfer semantics, where transfer operations are replicated the resources indicated by the links optionally selected using URI parameters. Group responses are aggregated using the SenML multi-item format.</t>

</section>
</section>
</section>
<section anchor="abstract-transfer-model" title="Abstract Transfer Model">

<t>The HSML media type assumes a transfer model capable of interacting with representations using a simple CRUD model, allowing for basic life cycle operations on resources and collections.</t>

<t><list style="hanging">
  <t hangText='CREATE'><vspace blankLines='0'/>
  Create an instance of a resource as specified using the payload as a constructor. Optionally return a reference to the created resource. Typically uses POST in CoAP or HTTP, may use PUBLISH in pubsub protocols.</t>
  <t hangText='RETRIEVE'><vspace blankLines='0'/>
  Obtain a representation of the selected resource. Typically uses GET in CoAP or HTTP, could use SUBSCRIBE with message retention in pubsub.</t>
  <t hangText='UPDATE'><vspace blankLines='0'/>
  Replace or partially replace the representation of the selected resource. Typically uses PUT or PATCH in CoAP and HTTP, could use PUBLISH in pubsub in the frequent case that CREATE and UPDATE are not needed on the same resource.</t>
  <t hangText='DELETE'><vspace blankLines='0'/>
  Remove the representation of the selected resource. Typically uses DELETE in CoAP or HTTP. There is no natural mapping to pubsub if a remove operation is not provided.</t>
  <t hangText='OBSERVE'><vspace blankLines='0'/>
  Obtain a sequence of representations of the selected resource, indicating state updates which occur on the resource. Typically uses CoAP Observe, HTTP EventSource, MQTT SUBSCRIBE. OBSERVE is the transfer equivalent of performing a RETRIEVE on the resource immediately following each state change of the resource.</t>
</list></t>

</section>
<section anchor="collection-description" title="Collections">

<section anchor="base-element" title="Base element">
<t>A base element describes the context under which to interpret values in items within the representation of a collection.</t>

<t>The base name value (bn) indicates the base URI or an absolute reference from which to base relative references found in the links. It functions as an embedded base URI reference as per <xref target="RFC3986"/> Section 5.1.1</t>

<t>The format of the base elements are specified in <xref target="I-D.ietf-core-senml"/>. <xref target="fig-example-base-element"/> is an example of a base  element.</t>

<figure title="Example Base Element" align="left" anchor="fig-example-base-element"><artwork><![CDATA[
    {
      "bn": "/dev/sen/"
    }
]]></artwork></figure>

<t>Other base items from SenML are permissible, including base time (bt) and base value(bv). If additional senml base element are present, the client MUST interpret the items in the collection in the context of the applicable base elements. For example, if there is a “bv” or base value elment, all of the returned values from items in the collection MUST be added to the base value as per <xref target="I-D.ietf-core-senml"/>.</t>

</section>
<section anchor="link-element" title="Link element">
<t>A link element is a hyperlink based on the structure and syntax of <xref target="RFC6690"/> and <xref target="I-D.ietf-core-links-json"/>. An example link element is shown in <xref target="fig-link-element"/>.</t>

<figure title="Example Link Element" align="left" anchor="fig-link-element"><artwork><![CDATA[
    {
      "href": "temp",
      "rt": "some.sensor"
    }
]]></artwork></figure>

</section>
<section anchor="item-element" title="Item element">
<t>An item element in a collection is a data element that is referenced by a link in the collection.</t>

<t>Items in the collection are indicated by a references (href) that serve as a selection variables for matching to URI parameters and resource names in multi-resource representataions. Reference resolution should use the rules defined in <xref target="RFC3986"/>.</t>

<t>Items may be embedded in the collection, they may be subresources of the collection, or they may be items in other collections referenced by links in the collection. An example item element is shown in <xref target="fig-item-element"/></t>

<figure title="Example Item Element" align="left" anchor="fig-item-element"><artwork><![CDATA[
    {
      "n": "temp",
      "v": "77"
    }
]]></artwork></figure>

</section>
</section>
<section anchor="representation-formats" title="Representation Formats">

<section anchor="example-formats" title="Example Serialization Formats">
<t><xref target="fig-example-hsml"/> shows an example document in hsml+json format. This example contains a base element, a link element, and an item element.</t>

<figure title="application/hsml+json Example" align="left" anchor="fig-example-hsml"><artwork><![CDATA[
    [
      {
        "bn": "/dev/sen/"
      },
      {
        "href": "temp",
        "rt": "some.sensor"
      },
      {
        "n": "temp",
        "v": "77"
      }
    ]
]]></artwork></figure>

</section>
</section>
<section anchor="uri-and-parameter-processing" title="URI and Parameter Processing">

<t>The HSML media type defines URI reference processing and URI Query processing but does not in general define fragment (#) references in URIs.</t>

<t>If fragment references are provided in a particular transfer implementation, they should be used to select single items in collections in accordance with current practice.</t>

<section anchor="uri-path-processing" title="URI Path Processing">

<t>The path part of the URI reference used to indicate HSML resources may be used as a reference to a collection or to an item in a collection. Collection references should contain the trailing slash character “/” in accordance with BCP. Server implementations should return links to collections with the trailing “/”, and should attempt to accept references to collections without the trailing “/” if such references can be used to construct unambiguous references.</t>

<t>References to items in a collection should not contain the trailing “/” character. Servers should return item references that do not contain the trailing “/” character, and should should attempt to accept references to items in collections with the trailing “/” if such references can be used to construct unambiguous references.</t>

<t>URI references may be routed to collections in the order in which path segments appear in the reference, from left to right reading the path string, separated by “/” characters.</t>

<t>URI references may alternatively be routed as opaque strings to resources. In this case, the resolution of relative references to items in a collection should be possible by concatenating the relative reference to the context URI of the collection. Note that this may enforce certain naming conventions such as the trailing slash in practice.</t>

</section>
<section anchor="uri-parameter-processing" title="URI Parameter processing">

<t>URI Parameters, typically mapped as query parameters in HTTP and CoAP, are used for selecting resources, selecting partial representations, and otherwise modifying aspects of the expected or included representation. In this way, they may be considered part of the URI, since they help identify a unique representation to be transferred.</t>

<section anchor="resource-selection" title="Resource selection">

<t>URI Parameters may be used to select resources in a collection for transfer. This is done using the common parameter matching rules specified in <xref target="RFC6690"/>.</t>

<t>Resource selection is performed based on matching URI Parameters with Link Parameters of all links in the collection which are exposed by the indicated media type and interface type. URI Parameters listed in <xref target="uri-params"/> are excluded from the matching process.</t>

</section>
</section>
</section>
<section anchor="transfer-model-mapping" title="Transfer Model Mapping">

<section anchor="collection" title="Collection">

<section anchor="retrieve" title="RETRIEVE">
<t>List Collection Elements</t>

</section>
<section anchor="create" title="CREATE">
<t>Add Elements to Collection</t>

</section>
<section anchor="update" title="UPDATE">
<t>Replace Entire Collection</t>

</section>
<section anchor="delete" title="DELETE">
<t>Remove Entire Collection</t>

</section>
</section>
<section anchor="links-1" title="Links">

<section anchor="retrieve-1" title="RETRIEVE">
<t>List Links</t>

</section>
<section anchor="create-1" title="CREATE">
<t>Add Links only</t>

</section>
<section anchor="update-including-partial-update" title="UPDATE (including partial update)">
<t>Modify Links</t>

</section>
<section anchor="delete-1" title="DELETE">
<t>Remove Links</t>

</section>
</section>
<section anchor="items" title="Items">

<section anchor="link-embedding-items" title="Link Embedding Items">

<t>Collective operations on items in collections are invoked by using the URI of the collections, along with URI parameters, to select one or more items in the collection.</t>

</section>
<section anchor="retrieve-2" title="RETRIEVE">
<t>Retrieve Items</t>

</section>
<section anchor="update-1" title="UPDATE">
<t>Modify Items</t>

</section>
<section anchor="delete-2" title="DELETE">
<t>Remove Items</t>

</section>
<section anchor="create-2" title="CREATE">
<t>Create Items with default links</t>

</section>
</section>
<section anchor="groups" title="Groups">

<t>Group transfer operations are provided by collections that contain links with the “grp” relation value.</t>

<t>Transfer operations which specify the collection URI as target are sent to the resolved URI of each link in the collection that contains the “grp” relation.</t>

<t>URI Parameters may be used to select a particular subset of target resources within the group in the collection.</t>

<t>Responses from the selected group resources are aggregated and by default returned as a single response. The group response SHOULD be returned as an outer array where such representation is available, for example a JSON array which contains elements consisting of SenML responses.</t>

<t>Optionally, a chunked response may be specified, if allowed by the transfer implementation, in which the response from each group member is returned individually as a sequence of responses.</t>

</section>
</section>
<section anchor="link-extensions" title="Link extensions">

<section anchor="actions" title="Actions">

<t>Actions are hypermedia controls used to construct transfer operations that change the state of resources. The use roughly follows the use of forms in HTML <xref target="RFC1866"/>, with semantics more consistent with links.</t>

<t>An example Action element is shown in <xref target="fig-action-element"/></t>

<figure title="Example Action Element" align="left" anchor="fig-action-element"><artwork><![CDATA[
    {
      "rel": "action"
      "type": "st.on"
      "href": "commands",
      "rt": "st.command",
      "method": "create",
      "accept": "text/plain",
      "schema": {"value": "on"}
    }
]]></artwork></figure>

</section>
<section anchor="monitors" title="Monitors">

<t>Monitors are hypermedia controls used to construct transfer operations that expose state changes of resources. A monitor invokes an outbound transfer operation on a target resource. Monitors use the IANA registered link relation “monitor”, defined in <xref target="RFC5989"/>.</t>

<t>An example Monitor element is shown in <xref target="fig-monitor-element"/></t>

<figure title="Example Monitor Element" align="left" anchor="fig-monitor-element"><artwork><![CDATA[
    {
      "rel": "monitor",
      "href": "tank-level-events",
      "content-type": "application/senml+json",
      "target-method": "create",
      "pmin": 600,
      "pmax": 3600,
      "nbul": 80,
      "nbll": 20
    }
]]></artwork></figure>

</section>
</section>
<section anchor="reserved-identifiers" title="Reserved Identifiers">

<t>This section defines the common reserved identifiers that are expected to be processed by implementations of HSML clients and servers. There are many more relation types and link parameters defined and registered with IANA. Implementations should not restrict processing to the keywords identified in this document; they should accept all IANA registered keywords as valid identifiers.</t>

<t>Many of the keywords listed are defined in other RFCs and IETF documents. This document does not redefine any existing keywords. Where a definition exists, the existing definition will be used. Where multiple conflicting definitions exist, this document will indicate the required definition.</t>

<t>New definitions are summarized in <xref target="iana-cons"/>.</t>

<section anchor="default-curie" title="Default CURIE">

<t>Identifiers in representations using the HSML media types are assumed to use the default CURIE “hsml”. An identifier that is not matched to an existing namespace is assumed to carry the prefix “hsml”.</t>

<t>For example, if the identifier “method” is encountered and it doesn’t resolve to an IANA registered parameter (reg-parameter in <xref target="RFC5988"/>) resolution should be attempted using “hsml:method”.</t>

<t>The default CURIE “hsml” identifies a namespace defined by the identifiers in <xref target="reserved-identifiers"/> of this document.</t>

</section>
<section anchor="uri-params" title="URI Processing Parameters">

<t>The following URI Parameters are used to filter representations according to specific processing rules and should not be used to attempt to match link parameters.</t>

<t><list style="hanging">
  <t hangText='“if”'>
  Interface type, used to select a partial representation of a collection</t>
  <t hangText='“count”'>
  Indicates the number of items to be returned from the collection</t>
  <t hangText='“start”'>
  Indicates the array index of the item in the collection to select as the first item to be returned</t>
  <t hangText='“page”'>
  Page number, in units of count</t>
</list></t>

</section>
<section anchor="link-keywords" title="Link Keywords">
<t>The following keywords are reserved for use in an HSML serialization to indicate elements of a web link</t>

<t><list style="hanging">
  <t hangText='“anchor”'><vspace blankLines='0'/>
  overrides the default resource context of the link</t>
  <t hangText='“rel”'><vspace blankLines='0'/>
  link relation type as defined in <xref target="RFC5988"/> and <xref target="RFC6690"/></t>
  <t hangText='“href”'><vspace blankLines='0'/>
  target of a link reference. This may be a relative reference in the collection e.g. “currentValue” or a local absolute reference “/sensors/temp/currentValue” or a full reference “https://example.com/sensors/temp/currentValue”</t>
</list></t>

<section anchor="link-relation-types" title="Link Relation Types">
<t>The following keywords are reserved for use in a HSML serialization to indicate types of link relations, and are used for values of “rel”.</t>

<t><list style="hanging">
  <t hangText='“self”'><vspace blankLines='0'/>
  refers to the collection that contains the link</t>
  <t hangText='“item”'><vspace blankLines='0'/>
  the link points to an item in the collection</t>
  <t hangText='“grp”'><vspace blankLines='0'/>
  the item the link points to is available for collective interaction through the collection URI according to group semantics described in {}</t>
</list></t>

</section>
<section anchor="link-attribute-types" title="Link Attribute Types">
<t>The following keywords are reserved for use in a HSML serialization to indicate types of link attributes</t>

<t><list style="hanging">
  <t hangText='“rt”'><vspace blankLines='0'/>
  the resource type(s) of the item</t>
  <t hangText='“u”'><vspace blankLines='0'/>
  units of measure</t>
  <t hangText='“ct”'><vspace blankLines='0'/>
  the CoAP content-format number(s) associated with the item</t>
  <t hangText='“content-type”'><vspace blankLines='0'/>
  the media type string(s) associated with the item</t>
  <t hangText='“obs”'><vspace blankLines='0'/>
  presence of this attribute indicates that the associated resource is observable</t>
</list></t>

</section>
</section>
<section anchor="item-keywords" title="Item Keywords">
<t>The following keywords are reserved for use in a HSML serialization to indicate elements within the serialization. These are defined in <xref target="I-D.ietf-core-senml"/>.</t>

<t><list style="hanging">
  <t hangText='“bn”'><vspace blankLines='0'/>
  the base name or base URI of the collection, relative to the service location e.g. “/sensors/temp/”</t>
  <t hangText='“bt”'><vspace blankLines='0'/>
  the base time that corresponds to the encapsulated state of the collection</t>
  <t hangText='“t”'><vspace blankLines='0'/>
  the time stamp that corresponds to the encapsulated state of the item in the collection, relative to the base time “bt”</t>
  <t hangText='“n”'><vspace blankLines='0'/>
  the name or URI of the resource, relative to the base name of the collection e.g. “currentValue”.</t>
  <t hangText='“u”'><vspace blankLines='0'/>
  units of measure</t>
  <t hangText='“v”'><vspace blankLines='0'/>
  number value</t>
  <t hangText='“vb”'><vspace blankLines='0'/>
  boolean value</t>
  <t hangText='“vo”'><vspace blankLines='0'/>
  object value, an extension to the senml value types to enable embedded data objects</t>
  <t hangText='“vs”'><vspace blankLines='0'/>
  string value</t>
</list></t>

</section>
<section anchor="link-parameters-used-in-actions" title="Link Parameters used in Actions">

<t><list style="hanging">
  <t hangText='“anchor”'><vspace blankLines='0'/>
  May override the default context of an action and store it in a different location from the subject resource</t>
  <t hangText='“rel”'><vspace blankLines='0'/>
  Indicates that this control is an action; MUST contain the value “action”</t>
  <t hangText='“href”'><vspace blankLines='0'/>
  URI for mapping the action specified in the action</t>
  <t hangText='“type”'><vspace blankLines='0'/>
  Additional indicator of the action being exposed, can be used with “rel”</t>
  <t hangText='“method”'><vspace blankLines='0'/>
  Transfer method to use on a particular action</t>
  <t hangText='“accept”'><vspace blankLines='0'/>
  The Content-Types or CoAP content-formats that are accepted on create and update methods</t>
  <t hangText='“content-type”'><vspace blankLines='0'/>
  The Content-Types that are exposed by retrieve and observe methods</t>
  <t hangText='“ct”'><vspace blankLines='0'/>
  the CoAP content-format number(s) exposed</t>
  <t hangText='“schema”'><vspace blankLines='0'/>
  Indicates the schema to use for constructing or interpreting transfer payloads, may be a literal value or a URI pointing to an instance of a schema</t>
</list></t>

</section>
<section anchor="link-parameters-used-in-monitors" title="Link Parameters used in Monitors">

<t><list style="hanging">
  <t hangText='“anchor”'><vspace blankLines='0'/>
  May override the context URI of a binding with any observable resource</t>
  <t hangText='“rel”'><vspace blankLines='0'/>
  Indicates that this control is a monitor; MUST contain the value “monitor”</t>
  <t hangText='“href”'><vspace blankLines='0'/>
  The URI of the resource used to monitor context URI, where transfer operations will be sent.</t>
  <t hangText='“accept”'><vspace blankLines='0'/>
  The media type string or CoAP content-format to request from the observed resource</t>
  <t hangText='“content-type”'><vspace blankLines='0'/>
  The media type string to use in the transfer operation</t>
  <t hangText='“ct”'><vspace blankLines='0'/>
  the CoAP content-format number to use in the transfer operation</t>
  <t hangText='“accept-method”'><vspace blankLines='0'/>
  Transfer method to use in request from the observed resource, default is OBSERVE</t>
  <t hangText='“target-method”'><vspace blankLines='0'/>
  Transfer method to use for notifications, default is UPDATE</t>
  <t hangText='“accept-schema”'><vspace blankLines='0'/>
  Schema to use in interpreting the observed resource payload, required if target-schema is used.</t>
  <t hangText='“target-schema”'><vspace blankLines='0'/>
  Schema to use in constructing the notification transfer payload, default is to transfer the accepted payload unmodified to the target resource.</t>
</list></t>

</section>
<section anchor="conditional-observe-parameters-used-in-monitor-links" title="Conditional Observe Parameters used in Monitor links">

<t><list style="hanging">
  <t hangText='“pmin”'><vspace blankLines='0'/>
  Minimum time between notification from a binding</t>
  <t hangText='“pmax”'><vspace blankLines='0'/>
  Maximum time between notifications from a binding</t>
  <t hangText='“gt”'><vspace blankLines='0'/>
  value to match or exceed to determine notification condition</t>
  <t hangText='“lt”'><vspace blankLines='0'/>
  value to match or be less than to determine notification condition</t>
  <t hangText='“st”'><vspace blankLines='0'/>
  value change +/- from last report to determine notification condition</t>
  <t hangText='“eq”'><vspace blankLines='0'/>
  value to match, or change from, to determine notification condition</t>
  <t hangText='“nbll”'><vspace blankLines='0'/>
  Defines a lower limit, at or above which notification is enabled</t>
  <t hangText='“nbul”'><vspace blankLines='0'/>
  Defines an upper limit, at or below which notification is enabled</t>
  <t hangText='“init”'><vspace blankLines='0'/>
  Starts the notification state machine with an initial value</t>
</list></t>

</section>
</section>
<section anchor="iana-cons" title="IANA Considerations">

<section anchor="new-media-types-for-iana-media-type-registry" title="New Media Types for IANA Media Type registry">

<t>Type</t>

<t><list style="symbols">
  <t>application</t>
</list></t>

<t>Subtypes</t>

<t><list style="symbols">
  <t>hsml</t>
  <t>hsml.collection</t>
  <t>hsml.link</t>
  <t>hsml.item</t>
</list></t>

<t>Media type strings</t>

<t><list style="symbols">
  <t>application/hsml</t>
  <t>application/hsml.collection</t>
  <t>application/hsml.link</t>
  <t>application/hsml.item</t>
  <t>application/hsml+json</t>
  <t>application/hsml.collection+json</t>
  <t>application/hsml.link+json</t>
  <t>application/hsml.item+json</t>
</list></t>

</section>
<section anchor="new-content-formats-for-the-iana-core-parameters-registry" title="New Content Formats for the IANA CoRE Parameters Registry">

<t>(subject to Structured Syntax encoding rules TBD)</t>

<t><list style="symbols">
  <t>22000 - application/hsml+json</t>
  <t>22001 - application/hsml.link+json</t>
  <t>22002 - application/hsml.item+json</t>
</list></t>

</section>
<section anchor="new-link-parameters" title="New Link Parameters">

<t><list style="symbols">
  <t>method</t>
  <t>schema</t>
  <t>content-type</t>
  <t>ct</t>
</list></t>

<t>The following should be registered in the CoRE dynamic linking draft <xref target="I-D.groves-core-dynlink"/>.</t>

<t><list style="symbols">
  <t>pmin</t>
  <t>pmax</t>
  <t>nbll</t>
  <t>nbul</t>
  <t>init</t>
  <t>lt</t>
  <t>gt</t>
  <t>st</t>
  <t>eq</t>
</list></t>

</section>
<section anchor="new-link-relation-types-rel" title="New Link Relation Types (rel=)">

<t><list style="symbols">
  <t>grp</t>
</list></t>

</section>
<section anchor="new-interface-types-if-for-the-iana-core-parameters-registry" title="New Interface types (if=) for the IANA CoRE Parameters Registry">

<t><list style="symbols">
  <t>hsml.collection</t>
  <t>hsml.item</t>
  <t>hsml.link</t>
</list></t>

</section>
</section>
<section anchor="security-considerations" title="Security Considerations">

<section anchor="object-signing" title="Object Signing">
<t>Collection representations are resource state encapsulations and may be transmitted and stored as signed objects in order to protect the integrity of data and metadata, including time and embedded access control information.</t>

</section>
<section anchor="signed-embedded-time-stamps" title="Signed Embedded Time Stamps">
<t>The collection may include time stamps (bt and t) that are signed with the object data and metadata.</t>

</section>
<section anchor="signed-embedded-access-control" title="Signed Embedded Access Control">
<t>The collection representation may include embedded access control information, also signed with the metadata, that can instruct the server to enforce a particular access policy for transfer requests.</t>

</section>
<section anchor="secure-state-updates" title="Secure State Updates">
<t>Representations submitted to a server to update the state of a resource (UPDATE, CREATE, DELETE) may also contain embedded signed assertions which may be used by the server to decide whether to apply or reject the update.</t>

</section>
<section anchor="object-signing-and-encryption" title="Object Signing and Encryption">
<t>Object signing and encryption SHOULD use the mechanisms specified in IETF documents for secure JSON Objects <xref target="RFC7516"/> and CBOR Objects <xref target="I-D.ietf-cose-msg"/>.</t>

</section>
</section>
<section anchor="design-patterns" title="Design Patterns">

<section anchor="restful-actuation-using-collections" title="RESTful Actuation using collections">

</section>
<section anchor="restful-events-and-alerts-using-collections" title="RESTful Events and Alerts using collections">

</section>
</section>


  </middle>

  <back>


    <references title='Informative References'>





<reference  anchor='RFC6690' target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc6690'>
<front>
<title>Constrained RESTful Environments (CoRE) Link Format</title>
<author initials='Z.' surname='Shelby' fullname='Z. Shelby'><organization /></author>
<date year='2012' month='August' />
<abstract><t>This specification defines Web Linking using a link format for use by constrained web servers to describe hosted resources, their attributes, and other relationships between links.  Based on the HTTP Link Header field defined in RFC 5988, the Constrained RESTful Environments (CoRE) Link Format is carried as a payload and is assigned an Internet media type.  &quot;RESTful&quot; refers to the Representational State Transfer (REST) architecture.  A well-known URI is defined as a default entry point for requesting the links hosted by a server.  [STANDARDS-TRACK]</t></abstract>
</front>
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='6690'/>
<seriesInfo name='DOI' value='10.17487/RFC6690'/>
</reference>



<reference anchor='I-D.ietf-core-links-json'>
<front>
<title>Representing CoRE Formats in JSON and CBOR</title>

<author initials='K' surname='Li' fullname='Kepeng Li'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='A' surname='Rahman' fullname='Akbar Rahman'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='C' surname='Bormann' fullname='Carsten Bormann'>
    <organization />
</author>

<date month='July' day='8' year='2016' />

<abstract><t>JavaScript Object Notation, JSON (RFC7159) is a text-based data format which is popular for Web based data exchange.  Concise Binary Object Representation, CBOR (RFC7049) is a binary data format which has been optimized for data exchange for the Internet of Things (IoT).  For many IoT scenarios, CBOR formats will be preferred since it can help decrease transmission payload sizes as well as implementation code sizes compared to other data formats.  Web Linking (RFC5988) provides a way to represent links between Web resources as well as the relations expressed by them and attributes of such a link.  In constrained networks, a collection of Web links can be exchanged in the CoRE link format (RFC6690).  Outside of constrained environments, it may be useful to represent these collections of Web links in JSON, and similarly, inside constrained environments, in CBOR.  This specification defines a common format for this.</t></abstract>

</front>

<seriesInfo name='Internet-Draft' value='draft-ietf-core-links-json-06' />
<format type='TXT'
        target='http://www.ietf.org/internet-drafts/draft-ietf-core-links-json-06.txt' />
</reference>



<reference  anchor='RFC3986' target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc3986'>
<front>
<title>Uniform Resource Identifier (URI): Generic Syntax</title>
<author initials='T.' surname='Berners-Lee' fullname='T. Berners-Lee'><organization /></author>
<author initials='R.' surname='Fielding' fullname='R. Fielding'><organization /></author>
<author initials='L.' surname='Masinter' fullname='L. Masinter'><organization /></author>
<date year='2005' month='January' />
<abstract><t>A Uniform Resource Identifier (URI) is a compact sequence of characters that identifies an abstract or physical resource.  This specification defines the generic URI syntax and a process for resolving URI references that might be in relative form, along with guidelines and security considerations for the use of URIs on the Internet.  The URI syntax defines a grammar that is a superset of all valid URIs, allowing an implementation to parse the common components of a URI reference without knowing the scheme-specific requirements of every possible identifier.  This specification does not define a generative grammar for URIs; that task is performed by the individual specifications of each URI scheme.  [STANDARDS-TRACK]</t></abstract>
</front>
<seriesInfo name='STD' value='66'/>
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='3986'/>
<seriesInfo name='DOI' value='10.17487/RFC3986'/>
</reference>



<reference  anchor='RFC5988' target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc5988'>
<front>
<title>Web Linking</title>
<author initials='M.' surname='Nottingham' fullname='M. Nottingham'><organization /></author>
<date year='2010' month='October' />
<abstract><t>This document specifies relation types for Web links, and defines a registry for them.  It also defines the use of such links in HTTP headers with the Link header field.  [STANDARDS-TRACK]</t></abstract>
</front>
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='5988'/>
<seriesInfo name='DOI' value='10.17487/RFC5988'/>
</reference>



<reference  anchor='RFC5989' target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc5989'>
<front>
<title>A SIP Event Package for Subscribing to Changes to an HTTP Resource</title>
<author initials='A.B.' surname='Roach' fullname='A.B. Roach'><organization /></author>
<date year='2010' month='October' />
<abstract><t>The Session Initiation Protocol (SIP) is increasingly being used in systems that are tightly coupled with Hypertext Transport Protocol (HTTP) servers for a variety of reasons.  In many of these cases, applications can benefit from being able to discover, in near real- time, when a specific HTTP resource is created, changed, or deleted. This document proposes a mechanism, based on the SIP Event Framework, for doing so.  [STANDARDS-TRACK]</t></abstract>
</front>
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='5989'/>
<seriesInfo name='DOI' value='10.17487/RFC5989'/>
</reference>



<reference  anchor='RFC7252' target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc7252'>
<front>
<title>The Constrained Application Protocol (CoAP)</title>
<author initials='Z.' surname='Shelby' fullname='Z. Shelby'><organization /></author>
<author initials='K.' surname='Hartke' fullname='K. Hartke'><organization /></author>
<author initials='C.' surname='Bormann' fullname='C. Bormann'><organization /></author>
<date year='2014' month='June' />
<abstract><t>The Constrained Application Protocol (CoAP) is a specialized web transfer protocol for use with constrained nodes and constrained (e.g., low-power, lossy) networks.  The nodes often have 8-bit microcontrollers with small amounts of ROM and RAM, while constrained networks such as IPv6 over Low-Power Wireless Personal Area Networks (6LoWPANs) often have high packet error rates and a typical throughput of 10s of kbit/s.  The protocol is designed for machine- to-machine (M2M) applications such as smart energy and building automation.</t><t>CoAP provides a request/response interaction model between application endpoints, supports built-in discovery of services and resources, and includes key concepts of the Web such as URIs and Internet media types.  CoAP is designed to easily interface with HTTP for integration with the Web while meeting specialized requirements such as multicast support, very low overhead, and simplicity for constrained environments.</t></abstract>
</front>
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='7252'/>
<seriesInfo name='DOI' value='10.17487/RFC7252'/>
</reference>



<reference  anchor='RFC7516' target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc7516'>
<front>
<title>JSON Web Encryption (JWE)</title>
<author initials='M.' surname='Jones' fullname='M. Jones'><organization /></author>
<author initials='J.' surname='Hildebrand' fullname='J. Hildebrand'><organization /></author>
<date year='2015' month='May' />
<abstract><t>JSON Web Encryption (JWE) represents encrypted content using JSON-based data structures.  Cryptographic algorithms and identifiers for use with this specification are described in the separate JSON Web Algorithms (JWA) specification and IANA registries defined by that specification.  Related digital signature and Message Authentication Code (MAC) capabilities are described in the separate JSON Web Signature (JWS) specification.</t></abstract>
</front>
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='7516'/>
<seriesInfo name='DOI' value='10.17487/RFC7516'/>
</reference>



<reference  anchor='RFC1866' target='http://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc1866'>
<front>
<title>Hypertext Markup Language - 2.0</title>
<author initials='T.' surname='Berners-Lee' fullname='T. Berners-Lee'><organization /></author>
<author initials='D.' surname='Connolly' fullname='D. Connolly'><organization /></author>
<date year='1995' month='November' />
<abstract><t>This document defines a HTML 2.0 (to distinguish it from the previous informal specifications).  [STANDARDS-TRACK]</t></abstract>
</front>
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='1866'/>
<seriesInfo name='DOI' value='10.17487/RFC1866'/>
</reference>



<reference anchor='I-D.ietf-core-interfaces'>
<front>
<title>Reusable Interface Definitions for Constrained RESTful Environments</title>

<author initials='Z' surname='Shelby' fullname='Zach Shelby'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='M' surname='Vial' fullname='Matthieu Vial'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='M' surname='Koster' fullname='Michael Koster'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='C' surname='Groves' fullname='Christian Groves'>
    <organization />
</author>

<date month='July' day='8' year='2016' />

<abstract><t>This document defines a set of reusable REST resource design patterns suitable for use in constrained environments, based on IETF CoRE standards for information representation and information exchange.  Interface types for Sensors, Actuators, Parameters, and resource Collections are defined using the "if" link attribute defined by CoRE Link Format [RFC6690].  Clients may use the "if" attribute to determine how to consume resources.  Editor's note: This version removes the observe notify functionality. Further work is needed on this draft to</t></abstract>

</front>

<seriesInfo name='Internet-Draft' value='draft-ietf-core-interfaces-05' />
<format type='TXT'
        target='http://www.ietf.org/internet-drafts/draft-ietf-core-interfaces-05.txt' />
</reference>



<reference anchor='I-D.ietf-core-resource-directory'>
<front>
<title>CoRE Resource Directory</title>

<author initials='Z' surname='Shelby' fullname='Zach Shelby'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='M' surname='Koster' fullname='Michael Koster'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='C' surname='Bormann' fullname='Carsten Bormann'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='P' surname='Stok' fullname='Peter Van der Stok'>
    <organization />
</author>

<date month='July' day='8' year='2016' />

<abstract><t>In many M2M applications, direct discovery of resources is not practical due to sleeping nodes, disperse networks, or networks where multicast traffic is inefficient.  These problems can be solved by employing an entity called a Resource Directory (RD), which hosts descriptions of resources held on other servers, allowing lookups to be performed for those resources.  This document specifies the web interfaces that a Resource Directory supports in order for web servers to discover the RD and to register, maintain, lookup and remove resources descriptions.  Furthermore, new link attributes useful in conjunction with an RD are defined.</t></abstract>

</front>

<seriesInfo name='Internet-Draft' value='draft-ietf-core-resource-directory-08' />
<format type='TXT'
        target='http://www.ietf.org/internet-drafts/draft-ietf-core-resource-directory-08.txt' />
</reference>



<reference anchor='I-D.ietf-core-senml'>
<front>
<title>Media Types for Sensor Markup Language (SenML)</title>

<author initials='C' surname='Jennings' fullname='Cullen Jennings'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='Z' surname='Shelby' fullname='Zach Shelby'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='J' surname='Arkko' fullname='Jari Arkko'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='A' surname='Keranen' fullname='Ari Keranen'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='C' surname='Bormann' fullname='Carsten Bormann'>
    <organization />
</author>

<date month='July' day='8' year='2016' />

<abstract><t>This specification defines media types for representing simple sensor measurements and device parameters in the Sensor Markup Language (SenML).  Representations are defined in JavaScript Object Notation (JSON), Concise Binary Object Representation (CBOR), eXtensible Markup Language (XML), and Efficient XML Interchange (EXI), which share the common SenML data model.  A simple sensor, such as a temperature sensor, could use this media type in protocols such as HTTP or CoAP to transport the measurements of the sensor or to be configured.</t></abstract>

</front>

<seriesInfo name='Internet-Draft' value='draft-ietf-core-senml-02' />
<format type='TXT'
        target='http://www.ietf.org/internet-drafts/draft-ietf-core-senml-02.txt' />
</reference>



<reference anchor='I-D.ietf-cose-msg'>
<front>
<title>CBOR Object Signing and Encryption (COSE)</title>

<author initials='J' surname='Schaad' fullname='Jim Schaad'>
    <organization />
</author>

<date month='June' day='23' year='2016' />

<abstract><t>Concise Binary Object Representation (CBOR) is data format designed for small code size and small message size.  There is a need for the ability to have the basic security services defined for this data format.  This document defines the CBOR Object Signing and Encyption (COSE) specification.  This specification describes how to create and process signature, message authentication codes and encryption using CBOR for serialization.  This specifiction additionally specifies how to representat cryptographic keys using CBOR.</t></abstract>

</front>

<seriesInfo name='Internet-Draft' value='draft-ietf-cose-msg-14' />
<format type='TXT'
        target='http://www.ietf.org/internet-drafts/draft-ietf-cose-msg-14.txt' />
</reference>



<reference anchor='I-D.groves-core-dynlink'>
<front>
<title>Dynamic Resource Linking for Constrained RESTful Environments</title>

<author initials='Z' surname='Shelby' fullname='Zach Shelby'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='M' surname='Vial' fullname='Matthieu Vial'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='M' surname='Koster' fullname='Michael Koster'>
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='C' surname='Groves' fullname='Christian Groves'>
    <organization />
</author>

<date month='July' day='6' year='2016' />

<abstract><t>For CoAP [RFC7252] Dynamic linking of state updates between resources, either on an endpoint or between endpoints, is defined with the concept of Link Bindings.  This document defines conditional observation attributes that work with Link Bindings or with simple CoAP Observe [RFC7641].</t></abstract>

</front>

<seriesInfo name='Internet-Draft' value='draft-groves-core-dynlink-00' />
<format type='TXT'
        target='http://www.ietf.org/internet-drafts/draft-groves-core-dynlink-00.txt' />
</reference>


<reference anchor="REST" target="http://www.ics.uci.edu/~fielding/pubs/dissertation/fielding_dissertation.pdf">
  <front>
    <title>Architectural Styles and the Design of Network-based Software Architectures</title>
    <author initials="R." surname="Fielding" fullname="Roy Thomas Fielding">
      <organization>University of California, Irvine</organization>
    </author>
    <date year="2000"/>
  </front>
  <seriesInfo name="Ph.D." value="Dissertation, University of California, Irvine"/>
  <format type="PDF" target="http://www.ics.uci.edu/~fielding/pubs/dissertation/fielding_dissertation.pdf"/>
</reference>
<reference anchor="W3C-WoT" target="https://www.w3.org/WoT/IG/">
  <front>
    <title>W3C Web of Things Interest Group</title>
    <author initials="." surname="WoT IG">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <date year="2016"/>
  </front>
</reference>
<reference anchor="T2TRG" target="https://datatracker.ietf.org/rg/t2trg/charter/">
  <front>
    <title>IRTF Thing to Thing Research Group</title>
    <author initials="." surname="IRTF">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <date year="2016"/>
  </front>
</reference>


    </references>




  </back>
</rfc>

