<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" []>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='http://xml.resource.org/authoring/rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="no"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc strict="no"?>
<?rfc compact="no"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>

<rfc category="std" ipr="trust200902" docName="draft-koster-core-coapmq-00.txt">

  <front>
  <title abbrev="Message Queueing in CoAP">Message Queueing in the Constrained Application Protocol (CoAP)</title>   

    <author fullname="Michael Koster" initials="M.K." surname="Koster">
      <organization>ARM Limited</organization>
      <address>
	    <email>Michael.Koster@arm.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    
    
    <author fullname="Ari Keranen" initials="A.K." surname="Keranen">
      <organization>Ericsson</organization>
      <address>
        <email>ari.keranen@ericsson.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
	
    <date year="2014"/>
    <keyword>Internet-Draft</keyword>
    <keyword>CORE</keyword>
    <keyword>CoAP</keyword>
    <keyword>Message Queueing</keyword>
    <abstract>

  <t>The CoRE Application Protocol (CoAP) and related specifications are intended to support machine-to-machine communication in systems where one or more nodes are resource constrained. The constrained resources may be electrical power, computing resources, network bandwidth, or network connectivity. The use case of constrained or limited network connectivity is envisioned by the base protocols but not well defined. This document specifies support of limited connectivity resource endpoints in CoAP and CoRE Resource Directory. This protocol extension specifies support for endpoints operated in a sleep-wakeup cycle mode and/or behind Network Address Translators (NATs).</t>
  
</abstract>

  </front>
  <middle>

<!-- ====================================================================== -->

<section anchor="introduction" title="Introduction">
   <t>IETF CoRE supports machine to machine communication across networks of constrained devices. One important class of constrained devices includes devices that are intended to run for years from a small battery, or by scavenging energy from their environment. These devices spend most of their time in a sleeping state with no network connectivity. Likewise, the devices may be located behind Network Address Translation (NAT) gateways, In these cases, the constrained endpoint node had limited network reachability. </t>

   <t>Nodes with limited reachability must communicate using a client role, whereby the endpoint is responsible for initiating communication, and indicating to the network when it has a data or state update to communicate.</t>

   <t>This document specifies the means for nodes with limited reachability to communicate reliably in constrained resource networks, using simple extensions to the CoAP REST API and CoRE Resource Directory.</t>

   <t>A message store-and-forward mode is specified to be implemented in a new core.mq function set which improves the reachability and performance of constrained endpoints in the system. A core.mq function server, which acts as a message store-and-forward broker and virtual endpoint, may be associated with one or more Resource Directories.</t>

   <t>New attributes are defined to enable discovery and configuration of the new function set.</t>
</section>

<!-- ====================================================================== -->

<section title="Terminology">
   <t>The key words 'MUST', 'MUST NOT', 'REQUIRED', 'SHALL', 'SHALL NOT',
   'SHOULD', 'SHOULD NOT', 'RECOMMENDED', 'MAY', and 'OPTIONAL' in this
   specification are to be interpreted as described in <xref target="RFC2119"/>.</t>
   
   <t>This specification requires readers to be familiar with all the terms and concepts that are discussed in <xref target="RFC5988"/> and <xref target="RFC6690"/>. Readers should also be familiar with the terms and concepts discussed in <xref target="I-D.ietf-core-coap"/> and <xref target="I-D.ietf-core-resource-directory"/>. The URI template format, see <xref target="RFC6570"/>, is used to describe the REST interfaces defined in this specification.</t>

   <t>This specification makes use of the following additional terminology:
<list style="hanging">

<t hangText="Resource Directory:">An web entity that stores information about web resources and implements the REST interfaces defined in this specification for registration and lookup of those resources.</t>

<t hangText="Endpoint:">An endpoint (EP) is a term used to describe a web server or client in <xref target="I-D.ietf-core-coap"/>. In the context of this specification an endpoint is used to describe a web server that registers resources to the Resource Directory. An endpoint is identified by its endpoint name, which is included during registration, and is unique within the associated domain of the registration.</t>

<t hangText="Reachable:">An endpoint is reachable if it is capable of responding to unsolicited CoAP requests required to implement the protocol. It is usually associated with having a routable IP address and a protocol listener. Not-reachable endpoints may still initiate requests and receive responses.</t>

<t hangText="NAT compatibility:">
A client-only interaction mode is supported to enable the endpoint to be situated behind NAT routers and gateways. In client mode, all interaction is initiated by the client behind the NAT router.</t>

<t hangText="Queueing:">Queueing mode is defined, whereby an endpoint, on waking up, may retrieve all pending messages which accumulated while the endpoint was sleeping. Queueing mode is optional and is indicated by the presence of the xx.queue attribute.</t>

<t hangText="Publish-Subscribe:">CoapMQ supports publish-subscribe pattern interactions, where an endpoint uses the core.mq function server as a broker, sending updates to be buffered and sent to zero or more subscribers. Likewise, an endpoint may register with a core.mq server to receive buffered updates published to the core.mq server by other endpoints. There is a simple binding of operations to pub-sub protocol operations, for example MQTT publish and subscribe operations.</t>

<t hangText="Class 0 node:">A node which contains very limited resources may be registered to a core.mq server and use the core.mq server as a proxy and virtual endpoint. The definition of a class 0 node is extended to include use cases where the endpoint node has limited power capability and/or limited reachability, in addition to potentially limited memory and processing capability. Devices of this type may be registered with the help of an external agent, power supply, or helper device.</t>

<t hangText="Sleeping endpoint support:">Once an endpoint is registered, it may sleep and wake up to send and receive data at appropriate times, such as when the sensor output changes, or at regular intervals. The sleep/wakeup times are expected to be at the discretion of the endpoint. The sleeping endpoint may signal it's wakeup times to the core.rd service in order to synchronize with the core.mq function service. Sleeping endpoint support requires that the endpoint be able to initiate all transactions, including entering and leaving sleep mode. </t>
</list>
</t>

 <t>The following entities are used in this specification:
<list style="hanging">

<t hangText="RD server:">A Resource Directory server (RD) is used to register the presence and network location of CoapMQ protocol capable endpoints. Endpoints wishing to use the CoapMQ protocol register with the RD server using a special set of attributes indicating use of the core.mq function set. The RD server supporting CoAP MQ registration is responsible for indicating the availability and location of the core.mq function set.</t>

<t hangText="Core.mq function server:">An endpoint at the service functions as a core.mq function server, interacting with the endpoint as needed to transfer data and state during active updates. The core.mq server may be controlled by endpoint interaction with an associated RD server.</t>

</list>
</t>

</section>
	  
<!-- ====================================================================== -->

<section anchor="architecture" title="Architecture"> 

<section title="RD Server with MQ function set">

<t><xref target="arch-fig"/> shows an example architecture of a CoapMQ capable service. A RD service accepts registrations and registration updates from endpoints and hosts a resource discovery service for web application clients. Cached state information is updated from the endpoints to the core.mq function server. Web clients subscribe to the state of the endpoint from the core.mq server, and publish updates to the endpoint state through the core.mq server. The core.mq server performs a store-and-forward function between the web client and the CoapMQ capable endpoint.</t>

        <t>
        <figure title="CoAP MQ Architecture" anchor="arch-fig">
          <artwork>
            <![CDATA[
 Endpoint                  Service                   Application
                           +------+
                           |      |
            +- register -> |  RD  | <- discover -+
 +------+   |              |      |              |   +--------+
 |      | --+              +------+              +-- |  Web   |
 |  EP  |                                            | Client |
 |      | <-+              +------+              +-> |  app   |
 +------+   |              |      |              |   +--------+
            +-- pub/sub -> |  MQ  | <- pub/sub --+
                           |      |
                           +------+
]]>
</artwork>
</figure>
</t>
</section>

<section title="Client Endpoint"> 
<t>Client endpoints initiate all interaction with the RD server and core.mq server. If the endpoint is an actuator it will need to either use GET + Observe or periodically poll the core.mq server using GET to check for updates. A client sensor would use PUT operations to update the core.mq function server. A client sensor should update the RD server periodically to indicate that it is still alive if it has no pending data updates. Endpoints can operate in client mode even if not directly reachable from the core.mq or core.rd servers.</t>
</section> 

<section title="Server endpoint">
<t>Server endpoints require the core.mq function sever to perform a client role, initiating interaction with the endpoint. This is a preferred mode when, for example, the endpoint is a sensor and wishes to update the core.mq function server periodically upon waking up between sleep intervals in response to a GET + Observe operation. In this mode an actuator endpoint would update the RD server to indicate waking mode and ready to receive updates. The core.mq client would then use PUT operations to update the server endpoint. Server mode endpoints are required to be reachable from the core.rd and core.mq function servers.</t>
</section>

</section> 

<!-- ====================================================================== -->

<section title="Registration and discovery - RD server"> 
<t>An endpoint wishing to use the CoapMQ protocol registers with an RD server that advertises the core.mq function set. The endpoint registers with the core.pubsub attribute to indicate intention to use the CoapMQ protocol.</t>

<section title="Register PubSub Endpoint">
<t><xref target="reg-fig"/> shows the flow of the registration operation. Discovery proceeds as per Resource Directory. When an endpoint wishes to use the CoapMQ protocol, it discovers the core.mq function set at the RD service and registers with the RD server by creating a RD endpoint and updating it with the core.pubsub attribute.</t>

        <t>
        <figure title="Discovery and Registration Message Exchange" anchor="reg-fig">
          <artwork>
            <![CDATA[
EP                                               MQ        RD
 |                  MQ DISCOVERY                 |         |
 | -------- GET /.well-known/core?rt=core.mq --- | ------> |
 |                                               |         |
 | <-------- 2.05 Content “</mq>; rt=core.mq”--- | ------- |
 |                                               |         |
 |                                               |         |
 |                  REGISTRATION                 |         |
 | ------------- POST /rd “</mq/0/…” ----------- | ------> |
 |                                               |         |
 | <-------- 2.01 Created Location: /rd/1234 --- | ------- |
 |                                               |         |
 |                                               |         |
]]>
</artwork>
</figure>
</t>
</section>

<section title="Unregister Endpoint">
<t>CoapMQ endpoints indicate the end of their registration tenure by either explicitly unregistering or allowing the lifetime of the previous registration to expire.</t> 
</section>

</section>

<!-- ====================================================================== -->


<section title="CoRE MQ Function Set">

<section title="core.mq subscribe to endpoint using GET+Observe, endpoint publishes notifications to the core.mq server">
<t>The server mode endpoint enables the core.mq server to act as a client and subscribe to a resource on the endpoint using GET + Observe. <xref target="sub-observe-fig"/> shows the flow of core.mq server subscribing to the endpoint. </t>

        <t>
        <figure title="GET+Observe Message Exchange" anchor="sub-observe-fig">
          <artwork>
            <![CDATA[
EP                                               MQ        RD
 |                                               |         |
 |                                               |         |
 |                SUBSCRIBE                      |         |
 | <------- GET /0/... Observe: Token:XX ------- |         |
 |                                               |         |
 |                 PUBLISH                       |         |
 | ---------- 2.05 Content Observe:10----------> |         |
 |                                               |         |
 |                 PUBLISH                       |         |
 | ---------- 2.05 Content Observe:12----------> |         |
 |                                               |         |
 |                 PUBLISH                       |         |
 | ---------- 2.05 Content Observe:15----------> |         |
 |                                               |         |
 |                                               |         |
]]>
</artwork>
</figure>
</t>

</section>

<section title="Endpoint subscribe to core.mq using GET+Observe, core.mq server publishes notifications to the endpoint"> 
<t>Client mode endpoint subscribes to resource at core.rd server using GET+Observe. Updates to the REST API at the core.rd server are published to the actuator using Observe response tokens. Client may update actuator or resource based on received values associated with responses.</t>

        <t>
        <figure title="Publish to the Endpoint" anchor="publish-fig">
          <artwork>
            <![CDATA[
EP                                               MQ        RD
 |                                               |         |
 |                                               |         |
 |                 SUBSCRIBE                     |         |
 | ------- GET /0/... Observe: Token:XX -------> |         |
 |                                               |         |
 |                  PUBLISH                      |         |
 | <---------- 2.05 Content Observe:10---------- |         |
 |                                               |         |
 |                  PUBLISH                      |         |
 | <---------- 2.05 Content Observe:12---------- |         |
 |                                               |         |
 |                  PUBLISH                      |         |
 | <---------- 2.05 Content Observe:15---------- |         |
 |                                               |         |
 |                                               |         |
]]>
</artwork>
</figure>
</t>
</section>

<section title="Endpoint publish to core.mq">
<t>Client mode endpoint uses PUT to update the sensor or property resource at the core.mq server.</t>

        <t>
        <figure title="PUT from EP Message Exchange" anchor="put-ep-fig">
          <artwork>
            <![CDATA[
EP                                               MQ        RD
 |                                               |         |
 |                                               |         |
 |                    PUBLISH                    |         |
 | ----------------- PUT /0/... ---------------> |         |
 |                                               |         |
 |                                               |         |
 | <--------------- 2.04 Changed---------------- |         |
 |                                               |         |
 |                                               |         |
]]>
</artwork>
</figure>
</t>
</section>


<section title="core.mq publish to endpoint">
<t>core.rd server may update server mode endpoint using PUT when REST API updates occur. Endpoint server may update actuator or resource.</t>

        <t>
        <figure title="PUT by MQ Message Exchange" anchor="put-mq-fig">
          <artwork>
            <![CDATA[
EP                                               MQ        RD
 |                                               |         |
 |                                               |         |
 |                    PUBLISH                    |         |
 | <---------------- PUT /0/... ---------------- |         |
 |                                               |         |
 |                                               |         |
 | ---------------- 2.04 Changed---------------> |         |
 |                                               |         |
 |                                               |         |
]]>
</artwork>
</figure>
</t>

</section>

<section title="Endpoint GET from core.mq server">
<t>Client mode endpoint may issue GET without Observe as needed to obtain state from the core.mq server.</t>

        <t>
        <figure title="GET from core.mq server Message Exchange" anchor="get-mq-fig">
          <artwork>
            <![CDATA[
EP                                               MQ        RD
 |                                               |         |
 |                                               |         |
 |                                               |         |
 | ---------------- GET /0/... ----------------> |         |
 |                                               |         |
 |                                               |         |
 | <--------------- 2.05 Content --------------- |         |
 |                                               |         |
 |                                               |         |
]]>
</artwork>
</figure>
</t>

</section> 

<section title="core.mq GET from endpoint">
<t>Core.mq server may issue GET without Observe as needed to obtain state update from the server mode endpoint.</t>

        <t>
        <figure title="GET from endpoint Message Exchange" anchor="get-ep-fig">
          <artwork>
            <![CDATA[
EP                                               MQ        RD
 |                                               |         |
 |                                               |         |
 |                                               |         |
 | <--------------- GET /0/... ----------------- |         |
 |                                               |         |
 |                                               |         |
 | ---------------- 2.05 Content --------------> |         |
 |                                               |         |
 |                                               |         |
]]>
</artwork>
</figure>
</t>

</section>
</section> 

<!-- ====================================================================== -->

<section title="Sleep-Wakeup Cycle">

<section title="Registration with lifetime > max sleep interval">
<t>TBD</t>
</section>

<section title="Signal using RD update to indicate wakeup at least once before lifetime">
<t>TBD</t>
</section>

<section title="ACK not received timeout unregister - CoRE Observe unregister method? timeout linked to max sleep, lifetime? 7.31 with Token?">
<t>TBD</t>
</section>

<section title="RD update wakeup triggers pending endpoint ops (GET, SUB, PUT), queued ops from core.mq server - can this handshake with update ACK?">
<t>TBD</t>
</section>

<section title="Simple publish without RD update, either PUT or Observe Notification. Should this also reset the lifetime timer?">
<t>TBD</t>
</section>

<section title="Example">
        <t>
        <figure title="Example Sleep-Wakeup Message Exchange" anchor="sleep-wakeup-fig">
          <artwork>
            <![CDATA[
EP                                               MQ        RD
 |                                               |         |
 |                                               |         |
 |                   MQ DISCOVERY                |         |
 | -------- GET /.well-known/core?rt=core.mq --- | ------> |
 |                                               |         |
 | <-------- 2.05 Content “</mq>; rt=core.mq”--- | ------- |
 |                                               |         |
 |                   REGISTRATION                |         |
 | ------------- POST /rd “</mq/0/…” ----------- | ------> |
 |                                               |         |
 | <-------- 2.01 Created Location: /rd/1234 --- | ------- |
 |                                               |         |
 |                                               |         |
 |                                               |         |
 |                 WAKEUP SIGNAL                 |         |
 |              UPDATE REGISTRATION              |         |
 | ---------------- PUT /rd/1234 --------------- | ------> |
 |                                               |         |
 |                    PUBLISH                    |         |
 | <---------------- PUT /0/... ---------------- |         |
 |                                               |         |
 | ---------------- 2.04 Changed---------------> |         |
 |                                               |         |
 |                   SUBSCRIBE                   |         |
 | <------- GET /0/... Observe: Token:XX ------- |         |
 |                                               |         |
 |                   PUBLISH                     |         |
 | ---- 2.05 Content Observe:10 Token:XX-------> |         |
 |                                               |         |
 |                  OK TO SLEEP                  |         |
 | <--------------- 2.04 Changed---------------- |         |
 |                                               |         |
 |                                               |         |
 |                   PUBLISH                     |         |
 | ---- 2.05 Content Observe:10 Token:XX-------> |         |
 |                                               |         |
 |                                               |         |
 |                    PUBLISH                    |         |
 | ----------------- PUT /0/... ---------------> |         |
 |                                               |         |
 | <--------------- 2.04 Changed---------------- |         |
 |                                               |         |
 |                                               |         |
]]>
</artwork>
</figure>
</t>
</section>
</section> 

<!-- ====================================================================== -->

<section title="MQTT Protocol Binding">

<t>TBD</t>
<!-- 7.1 Topic mapping to path
7.2 MQTT client Subscribe to CoAP MQ resource
7.X CoAP MQ resource publish to (broker) subscribed MQTT client
7.X MQTT client Publish to CoAP MQ resource
--> 

</section>


 
<!-- ====================================================================== -->

<section anchor="SecurityConsiderations" title="Security Considerations">
  <t>TBD</t>
</section> 


<!-- ====================================================================== -->
<!-- 
<section anchor="PrivacyConsiderations" title="Privacy Considerations">
  <t>TBD</t>
</section>
--> 
<!-- ====================================================================== -->

<section anchor="iana" title="IANA Considerations">
<t>TBD</t>
</section> 

<!-- ====================================================================== -->

    
<section anchor="acks" title="Acknowledgements">
  <t>Add your name here.</t>
</section>


  </middle>

<!-- ====================================================================== -->
  <back>

    <references title="Normative References"> 
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6690"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6570"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.I-D.ietf-core-resource-directory"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.I-D.ietf-core-coap"?>
    </references> 

    <references title="Informative References"> 
	      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5988"?>
    </references>
  
  </back>

</rfc>
